Sigmund Freud Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Sigmund Freud Papers circa 6th century BCE-1998 CE 1871-1939 CE
MSS39990
Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939
48,600 items
141 containers plus 20 oversize and 3 artifacts
70.4 linear feet
23 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Founder of psychoanalysis. Correspondence, holograph and typewritten drafts of writings by Freud and others, family papers, patient case files, legal documents, estate records, receipts, military and school records, certificates, notebooks, a pocket watch, a Greek statue, an oil portrait painting, genealogical data, interviews, research files, exhibit material, bibliographies, lists, photographs and drawings, newspaper and magazine clippings, and other printed matter. The collection documents many facets of Freud's life and writings; his associations with family, friends, mentors, colleagues, students, and patients; and the evolution of psychoanalytic theory and technique.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Abraham, Karl, 1877-1925--Correspondence.; Adler, Alfred, 1870-1937--Correspondence.; Alexander, Franz, 1891-1964--Correspondence.; Andreas-Salomé, Lou, 1861-1937--Correspondence.; Bernays family--Correspondence.; Bernays, Anna Freud, 1858-1955--Interviews.; Bernays, Minna--Correspondence.; Binswanger, Ludwig, 1881-1966--Interviews.; Bonaparte, Marie, Princess, 1882-1962--Correspondence.; Breuer, Josef, 1842-1925--Correspondence.; Brill, A. A. (Abraham Arden), 1874-1948--Correspondence.; Brunswick, Ruth Mack--Correspondence.; Charcot, J. M. (Jean Martin), 1825-1893--Correspondence.; Deutsch, Felix, 1884-1964--Interviews.; Eastman, Max, 1883-1969--Correspondence.; Eckstein, Emma--Correspondence.; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955--Correspondence.; Eissler, K. R. (Kurt Robert), 1908-1999--Interviews.; Eitingon, M. (Max), 1880-1943--Correspondence.; Ferenczi, Sándor, 1873-1933--Correspondence.; Fliess, Wilhelm, 1858-1928--Correspondence.; Fluss, Emil--Correspondence.; Freud family--Correspondence.; Freud family.; Freud, Amalia, 1835-1929--Correspondence.; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982--Correspondence.; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982--Interviews.; Freud, Ernestine Drucker--Interviews.; Freud, Ernst L., 1892-1970--Correspondence.; Freud, Harry, 1909-1968--Interviews.; Freud, Martha, 1861-1951--Correspondence.; Freud, Martin--Correspondence.; Freud, Oliver, 1891-1969--Correspondence.; Freud, Oliver, 1891-1969--Interviews.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939--Portraits.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939.; Frink, Angelika, approximately 1884-1969.; Graf, Max, 1873-1958--Interviews.; Halberstadt, Sophie Freud, 1893-1920--Correspondence.; Heller, Judith Bernays--Interviews.; Hitschmann, Eduard, 1871-1957--Correspondence.; Hitschmann, Eduard, 1871-1957--Interviews.; Hollitscher, Mathilde Freud, 1887-1978--Correspondence.; Jackson, Edith Banfield, 1895-1977--Interviews.; Jekels, Ludwig, 1867-1954--Interviews.; Jones, Ernest, 1879-1958--Correspondence.; Jung, C. G. (Carl Gustav), 1875-1961--Correspondence.; Koller, Carl, 1857-1944--Correspondence.; Laforgue, René--Correspondence.; Lampl-de Groot, Jeanne--Correspondence.; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955--Correspondence.; Pankejeff, Sergius, 1887-1979--Correspondence.; Pankejeff, Sergius, 1887-1979--Interviews.; Pfister, Oskar, 1873-1956--Correspondence.; Pfister, Oskar, 1873-1956--Interviews.; Rank, Otto, 1884-1939--Correspondence.; Reik, Theodor, 1888-1969--Correspondence.; Reik, Theodor, 1888-1969--Interviews.; Riviere, Joan, 1883-1962--Correspondence.; Riviere, Joan, 1883-1962--Interviews.; Sachs, Hanns, 1881-1947--Correspondence.; Sarasin, Philipp, 1888-1968--Interviews.; Schur, Max.; Silberstein, Eduard, 1856-1925--Correspondence.; Simmel, Ernst, 1882-1947--Correspondence.; Stekel, Wilhelm, 1868-1940--Correspondence.; Struck, Hermann, 1876-1944--Correspondence.; Swoboda, Hermann, 1873-1962--Correspondence.; Viereck, George Sylvester, 1884-1962--Correspondence.; Weiss, Edoardo, 1889-1939--Correspondence.; Weiss, Edoardo, 1889-1939--Interviews.; Zweig, Arnold, 1887-1968--Correspondence.
Organizations
Allgemeines Krankenhaus (Vienna, Austria); Bellevue Sanatorium (Kreuzlingen, Switzerland)
Subjects
Goethepreis der Stadt Frankfurt am Main.; Hospitals--Austria--Vienna.; Medicine--Practice--Austria--Vienna.; Psychiatric hospitals--Switzerland--Kreuzlingen.; Psychoanalysis--Societies, etc.; Psychoanalysis.
Places
Austria--Emigration and immigration.; England--Emigration and immigration.
Titles
Sigmund Freud collection; Sigmund Freud papers and collection; Sigmund Freud Papers at the Library of Congress
Occupations
Psychoanalysts.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Sigmund Freud, founder of psychoanalysis, were given to the Library of Congress by the Sigmund Freud Archives between 1952 and 2018. Additional material was given to the Library between 1970 and 1976 by Anna Freud who subsequently bequeathed to the Sigmund Freud Archives the remainder of her father's papers in her possession at the time of her death in 1982. The archives deposited these papers in the Library of Congress in 1986 and converted the deposit to a gift in 2000. Numerous other donors gave material directly to the Library of Congress between 1942 and 2017. Further items were acquired by the Library through purchase, transfer, and exchange between 1943 and 2009.
Additional Guides
Descriptions of the Sigmund Freud Papers appear in Library of Congress Acquisitions: Manuscript Division, 1985, pp. 27-31, and Library of Congress Acquisitions: Manuscript Division, 1986, pp. 33-36.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Books have been transferred to the Rare Book and Special Collections Division. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Motion picture films and audio recordings of interviews have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Sigmund Freud Papers.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on twenty-three reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Online Content
Part of the papers of Sigmund Freud is available on the Library of Congress Web site at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000051. Digitization of this collection was made possible by The Polonsky Foundation. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the online edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1856, May 6 Born Sigismund Schlomo Freud, Freiberg, Moravia
1860 Moved with family to Vienna, Austria
1873 Graduated summa cum laude, Leopoldstädter Kommunal-Real-und Obergymansium, Vienna, Austria
1875 Changed first name to Sigmund
1876 1882 Conducted research on the nervous system at Ernst Brücke's Institute of Physiology, Vienna, Austria
1879 1880 Fulfilled compulsory military service
1881 M.D., University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria
1882 Clinical assistant in Hermann Nothnagel's Department of Internal Medicine, General Hospital, Vienna, Austria Met and became engaged to Martha Bernays
1883 Worked in Theodor Meynert's psychiatric clinic, General Hospital, Vienna, Austria
1884 Joined Department of Nervous Diseases, General Hospital, Vienna, Austria Began studying the effects and potential medical uses of cocaine
1885 Appointed lecturer in neuropathology, University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria Received grant to study neuropathology with Jean-Martin Charcot in Paris, France
1886 Established private practice, Vienna, Austria Married Martha Bernays
1887 Began corresponding with Wilhelm Fliess
1889 Traveled to Nancy, France, to study Hippolyte Bernheim's hypnotic techniques
1891 Established residence and office at Bergasse 19, Vienna, Austria, where he would remain until 1938
1892 Treated “Elizabeth von R.” (Ilona Weiss) in what Freud described as his first full length analysis of hysteria
1895 Published with Josef Breuer Studien über Hysterie [ Studies in Hysteria ] (Leipzig: F. Deuticke. 269 pp.)
1896 First used the term “psychoanalysis”
1900 Published Die Traumdeutung [ The Interpretation of Dreams ] (Leipzig: F. Deuticke. 371 pp.)
1901 Published Zur Psychopathologie des Alltagslebens [ Psychology of Everyday Life ] (Berlin: S. Karger. 80 pp.)
1902 Founded the Psychologische Mittwoch-Gesellschaft (renamed the Wiener Psychoanalytische Vereinigung in 1908) Appointed Professor Extraordinarius, University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria
1905 Published “Bruchstück einer Hysterie-Analyse” (“Dora” case study), Monatsschrift für Psychiatrie und Neurologie, 18:285-310 Published Der Witz und seine Beziehung zum Unbewussten [ Jokes and Their Relation to the Unconscious ] (Vienna: F. Deuticke. 205 pp.) Published Drei Abhandlungen zur Sexualtheorie [ Three Contributions to the Sexual Theory ] (Leipzig: F. Deuticke. 83 pp.)
1908 First International Congress of Psychoanalysis, Salzburg, Austria
1909 Lectured on psychoanalysis at Clark University, Worcester, Mass. Published “Analyse der Phobie eines fünfjährigen Knaben” (“Little Hans” case study), Jahrbuch für psychoanalytische und psychopathologische Forschungen, 1:1-109 Published “Bemerkungen über einen Fall von Zwangsneurose” (“Rat Man” case study), Jahrbuch für psychoanalytische und psychopathologische Forschungen, 1:357-421
1910 Published Über Psychoanalyse [ The Origin and Development of Psychoanalysis ] (Vienna: F. Deuticke. 62 pp.)
1912 Establishment of the “Committee,” a group composed of Freud's closest associates including Karl Abraham, Sándor Ferenczi, Ernest Jones, Otto Rank, and Hanns Sachs who consulted regularly on issues relating to Freud and the psychoanalytic movement
1913 Published Totem und Tabu: einige Übereinstimmungen im Seeleben der Wilden und der Neurotiker [ Totem and Taboo ] (Leipzig: H. Heller. 149 pp.)
1918 Published “Aus der Geschichte einer infantilen Neurose” (“Wolf-Man”case study), Sammlung kleiner Schriften zur Neurosenlehre IV (Vienna: F. Deuticke. 139 pp.)
1920 Published Jenseits des Lustprinzips [ Beyond the Pleasure Principle ] (Vienna: Internationaler Psychoanalytischer Verlag. 60 pp.)
1923 Diagnosed with cancer of the jaw and palate Published Das Ich und das Es [ The Ego and the Id ] (Vienna: Internationaler Psychoanalytischer Verlag. 77 pp.)
1930 Awarded the Goethe Prize by the city of Frankfurt, Germany Published Das Unbehagen in der Kultur [ Civilization and Its Discontents ] (Vienna: Internationaler Psychoanalytischer Verlag. 136 pp.)
1931 Bronze plaque erected by the city of Príbor, Czechoslovakia (formerly Freiberg, Moravia) at Freud's birthplace
1933 Published with Albert Einstein Warum Krieg? [ Why War? ] (Paris: International Institute of Intellectual Cooperation. 61 pp.)
1938 Left Vienna, Austria, and settled in London, England
1939 Published Der Mann Moses und die monotheistische Religion [ Moses and Monotheism ] (Amsterdam: A. de Lange. 241 pp.)
1939, Sept. 23 Died, London, England
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Sigmund Freud (1856-1939) span the years from about the 6th century BCE to 1998, with the bulk of material dating from 1871 to 1939. The collection documents Freud's founding of psychoanalysis including the birth and maturation of psychoanalytic theory, the refinement of its clinical technique, and the proliferation of its adherents and critics. Many facets of Freud's life and work are featured including his early medical and clinical training; his relationship with family, friends, colleagues, students, and patients; his association with early psychoanalytic societies; his perspectives on analytical training; and his numerous writings. The collection includes family papers, correspondence, holograph and typewritten drafts of writings, patient case files, legal documents, estate records, receipts, military and school records, certificates, notebooks, a pocket watch, a Greek statue, genealogical data, interviews, research files, exhibit material, bibliographies, lists, photographs and drawings, newspaper and magazine clippings, and other printed matter. The papers are arranged in ten series: Family Papers, General Correspondence, Subject File, Writings, Supplemental File, Interviews and Recollections, Additions, Artifacts and Painting, Closed, and Oversize. They are, for the most part, in German, English, and French.
The bulk of the collection consists of original documents, photocopies and other facsimiles, transcripts, English translations, and published editions collected and given to the Library of Congress by the Sigmund Freud Archives. The archives was founded in 1951 by a group of New York analysts, including K. R. Eissler, Heinz Hartmann, Ernst Kris, Bertram David Lewin, and Herman Nunberg, to collect Freud letters and writings which were at risk of being lost or destroyed in the aftermath of World War II. Because Freud did not retain copies of his outgoing correspondence, letters written by him were geographically dispersed among his many correspondents. The archives succeeded in obtaining original Freud material through gifts, most notably Anna Freud's bequest, and through purchase. When unable to acquire original documents, it solicited copies, transcripts, translations, and printed editions.
The Family Papers series contains Freud's correspondence with members of the Freud and Bernays families. Included are exchanges with his mother Amalia Freud, his wife Martha Freud, and their children Ernst L., Martin, Mathilde Freud Hollitscher, Oliver, Sophie Freud Halberstadt, and Anna, the only one of Freud's children to become a psychoanalyst. Among Freud's correspondence with his wife are a series of courtship letters or “brautbriefe” written on an almost daily basis between 1882 and 1886. The letters detail Freud's activities, associations, and aspirations during the period following his graduation from medical school to the establishment of his private practice in Vienna. Extensive correspondence with his sisters, brothers, nieces, nephews, grandchildren, and in-laws reveals the part played by Freud as paternal head of a large and extended family. Among these letters is correspondence between Freud and Minna Bernays, his sister-in-law and close confidante. The series also contains correspondence between individual family members other than Freud as well as correspondence between family members and persons outside the family. Included are letters by several prominent individuals including Princess Marie Bonaparte, Ruth Mack Brunswick, C. G. Jung, and Otto Rank. A subject file containing legal documents, certificates, estate records, school records, writings, and printed matter also relates to Freud's family.
The General Correspondence series features Freud's correspondence with friends, mentors, colleagues, students, and patients spanning seven decades from his school days to his death in 1939. Nearly six hundred correspondents are represented in the series. At times, their correspondence is limited to a single letter to or from Freud. In other cases, the correspondence is extensive, revealing Freud as a prolific correspondent who frequently chastised others for a lack of similar diligence. The earliest of such correspondence consists of Freud's adolescent letters to friends Eduard Silberstein and Emil Fluss while a student at the Leopoldstädter gymansium and the University of Vienna. Freud's subsequent correspondence includes letters from individuals who influenced his early work including Josef Breuer and J. M. Charcot.
The formative years of Freud's psychoanalytic theories is detailed in his correspondence with Berlin physician Wilhelm Fliess. Beginning in 1887 and continuing until just after Freud's break with Fliess in 1902, these letters are among the more revealing in the collection. The series also contains Freud's correspondence with many of his earliest adherents, some of whom also later broke with him. The letters trace the development of a psychoanalytic movement that coalesced around Freud in the years following his break with Fliess. Included is correspondence with Karl Abraham, Alfred Adler, Franz Alexander, A. A. Brill, M. Eitingon, Sándor Ferenczi, Eduard Hitschmann, Ernest Jones, C. G. Jung, Oskar Pfister, Otto Rank, Theodor Reik, Hanns Sachs, Ernst Simmel, Wilhelm Stekel, and Edoardo Weiss, among many others. The Abraham, Brill, Eitingon, Jones, Jung, Pfister, and Reik correspondence includes original Freud letters. Prominent women in the field represented in the series include Lou Andreas-Salmoné, Ruth Mack Brunswick, Emma Eckstein, Jeanne Lampl-de Groot, and Joan Riviere. Princess Marie Bonaparte's correspondence with Freud is located in her papers in the Manuscript Division. Notable among Freud's patients with whom he corresponded is Sergius Pankejeff whom Freud referred to as the “Wolf-Man.” Other prominent correspondents include Albert Einstein with whom Freud corresponded on the nature of war, Carl Koller who shared Freud's interest in the medical uses of cocaine, and novelist and essayist Thomas Mann.
The Subject File series includes patient case files from the Allgemeines Krankenhaus in Vienna and the Bellevue Sanatorium in Kreuzlingen, Switzerland, largely during the 1880s. Copies of book annotations and marginalia by Freud provide glimpses into the development of his theories. His career is highlighted in a large file of newspaper and magazine clippings as well as material concerning the Goethe Prize he received in 1930 and the Nobel Prize which he coveted but never received. Calendars kept by Freud record his daily activities from 1916 to 1918. Freud's early life is documented by biographical data, birth and marriage certificates, and gymnasium, university, and military records. His departure from Nazi-controlled Austria and immigration to London in 1938 is tracked through American diplomatic cables and newspaper clippings. The series also contains letters and telegrams written on his death just over a year after his arrival in England.
The Writings series contains holograph and typewritten drafts, galley proofs, offprints, and published copies of many of Freud's writings. Because of the large format of many of these items, the material has been filed in the Oversize series. The writings range chronologically from an 1877 article on his early research on eels to portions of his last major work, Der Mann Moses und die monotheistische Religion, published shortly before his death. Included in the series are articles, case histories, portions of books, published letters, lecture notes, prefaces, introductions, a travel journal, chronologies, obituaries, bibliographic notes, and casual jottings. The writings are arranged and described largely according to the bibliographic sequence established by James Strachey in Indexes and Bibliographies, volume 24 of The Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Works of Sigmund Freud (London, 1974) and, for works published after 1974, by Ingeborg Meyer-Palmedo and Gerhard Fichtner, Freud-Bibliographie mit Werkkonkordanz (Frankfurt am Main, 1989).
The Supplemental File series consists of material about Freud's life and work written or collected by Freud associates and scholars. The bulk of the material dates after Freud's death. Apart from articles and other writings, the series includes material related to observances in 1956 of the centenary of Freud's birth; Norman Kiel's compilation of contemporary and posthumous reviews of Freud's published works; and a medical file comprising correspondence, notes, and case histories by Hans Pichler and Max Schur relating to Freud's illness with cancer. Lists and research guides include Gerhard Fichtner's bibliographies, chronologies, lists, and inventories of Freud's correspondence and writings. Also included are auction catalogs listing the sale of Freudiana and lists of Freud's lectures and students at the University of Vienna. Miscellany at the end of the series consists primarily of printed matter including a clipping file dated largely between 1954 and 1979 which traces scholarly and popular treatment of Freud in the decades following his death.
The Interviews and Recollections series was compiled by K. R. Eissler, a founder and longtime secretary of the Sigmund Freud Archives. Hundreds of Eissler's interviews with Freud's associates, patients, and family are included in the series, most of them conducted in the 1950s. The series contains transcripts, some with corrections by the interviewee, and summaries of interviews, usually made when the subject requested that the interview not be tape recorded. Audio recordings that were made have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. Among those interviewed by Eissler are family members Anna Freud Bernays, Anna Freud, Ernestine Drucker Freud, Harry Freud, Oliver Freud, Judith Bernays Heller, and prominent associates such as Franz Alexander, Ludwig Binswanger, Felix Deutsch, Eduard Hitschmann, Edith Banfield Jackson, Ludwig Jekels, Sergius Pankejeff, Oskar Pfister, Theodor Reik, Joan Riviere, Philipp Sarasin, Hermann Swoboda, and Edoardo Weiss. Also included in the series are recollections about Freud contained in letters, writings, and notes either addressed to or collected by Eissler.
Artifacts in the collection consist of Freud's pocket watch which he gave to his personal physician Max Schur and a small Greek statue which Freud kept on his desk and later gave to Angelika Frink. The collection also includes an oil portrait of Freud.
An Additions series consists largely of supplemental material added to the collection in 2010. Included are photographs, wall text, and captions from exhibits commemorating the centenary of Freud's birth and an index to the standard edition of Freud's works. Files from the work of Herman and Margarete Nunberg include a history of the "Rat man" case and English translations by Margarete Nunberg of Freud's correspondence with Princess Marie Bonaparte, René Laforgue, and others. Photocopies of Freud's correspondence with writer Arnold Zweig, which were derestricted in 2010, are also present. The legibility of the photocopies varies considerably. A 2019 addition includes a letter from Freud to Paul Federn in 1913, in which he outlines his life history, and letters from Freud to Heinz Hartmann, 1927-1939, copies of which are in the General Correspondence series.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in ten series:
Family Papers, 1851-1978
General Correspondence, 1887-1996
Subject File, 1856-1988
Writings, 1877-1985
Supplemental File, 1765-1998
Interviews and Recollections, 1914-1998
Additions, 1912-1977
Artifacts and Painting, circa 6th century BCE-1936 CE
Closed, 1952-1956
Oversize, 1859-1985
Container List
- Family Papers, 1851-1978 (Box 1-14)
  - Correspondence with Sigmund Freud, 1876-1974 (Box 1-12)
    Correspondence between Sigmund Freud and members of the Freud and Bernays families. Some of the correspondence is accompanied by explanatory letters and notes.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of family member and therein chronologically.
    - Bernays, Anna Freud (sister), 1896, 1928, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Bernays, Edward L. (nephew)
      - Originals, 1925
      - Photocopies and transcripts
        - 1919-1921
        - 1922-1924
        - 1925-1931
    - Bernays, Eli (brother-in-law), 1900, 1919
    - Bernays, Emmeline and Minna (mother-in-law and sister-in-law)
      - 1882, Oct.-1886, May
      - 1886, June-Dec.
      - 1887, Jan.-May
      - 1887, June-Dec., 1896, 1898